this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at SC Radio dotnet.
SC radio is brought to you by the I Triple E Computer Society,
I Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash softball.
digitalocean is the easiest cloud.
platform to deploy, manage and scale applications of any size, removing infrastructure friction and providing predictability.
so developers and their teams can deploy faster and focus on building software that customers love.
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in an active community, we provide the support you need.
digitalocean stands out of the crowd due to its simplicity and high performance, with no billing surprises.
try digitalocean for free by getting a 100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco / SC radio.
this is Nate black for software engineering radio.
my topic today is the elixir programming language, and my guest is Sascha uric, the author of elixir in action.
sasha is a professional programmer with many years of experience writing desktop and.
web applications in various languages including elixir, err lang, Ruby, JavaScript, c-sharp and. C++.
his blog the Earl Angeles covers air lang, elixir and other programming related topics.
currently he writes elixir software for air cloak.
Sasha welcome to software engineering radio.
hi Nathan, thank you for having me here.
we're going to cover a lot of ground today, so I wanted to give a brief road map for you and for our listeners.
so the elixir programming language, first we're going to give a background and talk about where elixir fits in with air lang.
and how it might relate to other programming languages.
and after we get the high level, I'd like to dive into details about the different features of the language.
and how certain things work in the language.
and once we have those building blocks, we can move on the conceptual things such as like how does an elixir programmer think about writing code.
and what are the big concepts of writing elixir code.
so first Sascha, let's talk about what is a lick sir.
okay so that's quite a tough question, and it is all obviously a programming language.
in theory elixir is a general-purpose programming language, so it's Turing complete.
and you can course invoke various functions of the operating systems.
but it's specialized in my opinion, it's sweet spot and it's niche so to speak would be building software systems.
and by software system I mean any piece of software that is running on some server.
and it has to run constantly and continuously, and it has to do many different things at any point in time.
so like typical web server would be an example of a software system, but not just web server.
it can also be like a database for example, chat BOTS and other kinds of things that we run on the backend side of things. so yeah.
elixir is like the language in my opinion suited and built for that particular challenge.
and that's in particular because the language targets the beam virtual machine, which is the virtual machine of the Erlang programming language.
so a leek series specifically compiles down to the beam byte code, and it doesn't try to hide that fact.
it doesn't treat beam as the implementation detail, and it doesn't treat our language implementation detail.
and Erlang and in particular beam is a runtime which is again built and fine-tuned for our software systems right.
so it's a specialized runtime that makes it very very special and unique.
and it makes some decisions and trade-offs are made in implementation which are very well suited for software systems.
as the expense of other kinds of software like maybe desktop applications or one of tools.
you said that elixir doesn't treat err lang and the bean virtual machine has an implementation detail, what what did you mean by that.
so what I mean is that for first of all like you have a types in elixir, and the elixir types of literally Erlang types.
then many not many but some things from the standard library which exist in Erlang we are not wrapped in a lecturer.
so you literally call our line functions.
and then there is a the big piece of Erlang which is called OTP.
and this is a framework and this is a way how we structure our systems in elixir and Ireland.
and the OTP is absolutely not like hidden or abstracted away, we use OTP to build our systems both in your lung and elixir.
and there is no some magical wrappers which try to hide effect.
ok I think I understood, let's see if I can summarize that correctly.
so at the the level of the language elixir can do some things with air ylang, like you can call an airline function.
and perhaps it looks slightly different than when you call a function and airline.
but it's the same thing as calling an airline function is that right.
precisely yes, you can call you can seamlessly call or lung code.
and the types of Erlang are also the types of Alex here right.
so there's no like some impedance mismatch or some magic in the list here which which it builds on top of or lung.
ok does the relationship also work in Reverse.
like if I wrote some functions in elixir could I import them somehow in airline and call those functions in airline.
you can call elixir code from our lung, it's currently like as far as I know it in check for a while it requires some improvisations.
but as far as I know there has been some work in progress to improve that.
in fact I mean like when I first started with Alex here it was about five years ago.
I was I actually was using elixir from the existing Erlang system.
and with some trickery it wasn't like completely automated, but I was able to combine the two and invoke elixir code from for long.
so one way or another it's possible.
and as far as I know the risks of course some work on the other length tool inside to improve that to make that easier.
okay so it sounds like the relationship is principal it can work both ways.
but generally speaking are people using it just in one way, are they mostly calling the airline code and libraries from elixir.
so my impression will be the most cases in most in most cases you call our lung code from elixir.
you can also have by the way like when you have an elixir project which is called mix project, the tool is called mix.
you can have both elixir and or lung sources in that project, we actually had that situation a few years ago.
and you can you can easily then call a elixir called from airlock.
but in most cases yes I would say that people usually call our lung quote from elixir less often the other way around.
we had a few shows I think that in the past on software engineering radio that I think might be irrelevant for our listeners to look at.
if they want more details about air ylang we had episode 89 Joe Armstrong on air Lang.
and he went into quite a bit of detail about the thinking behind that system.
and we also had a several shows on the Scala programming language and one on akka, so that was episode 62 Scala.
in which we talked a lot about functional programming and the details of Scala.
so I think there might be relevant for listeners, and also the akka system which discusses an implementation in Java.
that is similar to the actor system or the the actor model that is exposed by airline.
so that's something maybe for our listeners to check out.
and Sasha I wanted to ask you if there is like a relationship or an analogy that we can draw with like the JVM.
and like the the relationship between Java and a language like Scala that compiles to the Java bytecode.
is their similarity their interrelationship with elixir and airline.
well I gotta first say that I'm not super familiar with Java and Scala or like closure for example.
but my impression is that relationship between elixir and Erlang is different than in say Java and for example closure.
or maybe closure is even a better example okay because elixir basically doesn't change semantics again.
it doesn't really try to invent a new paradigm or build some kind of different way.
of a completely different way which isn't necessarily suited or envisioned when the runtime has been built right.
so when you have for example closure, closure builds functional programming language.
the original language for JVM Java is not functional, it's object-oriented language.
and therefore closure has to have some impedance mismatch right simply by definition.
because it's a completely different paradigm and it has completely different rules.
with Erlang and elixir you don't have so much, they are very semantically I like to say that they are very close.
there are some differences I would say that they are in my opinion there are mostly minor differences.
but for the most part I like to think that elixir and/or langar almost like the same thing.
I mean obviously there are different languages with different syntax.
and beyond syntax they have some different toolings in the language and around language, but for the most part I treat them is very similar languages.
so that's one thing which is very special I would say in the relationship between elixir and our line.
if I will have to draw a comparison maybe a better comparison could be like sort of c-sharp and visual basic.net.
although even that's not a fair comparison but it's more like that.
in there's more similarity between Alex run along then I would say languages which I've seen on the JVM.
okay thanks thanks for that clarification, yeah that makes that makes sense.
so because they're conceptually or in terms of their semantics just the way that the language works.
so think about it like this for example, as far as I've heard like again I'm no expert.
you have like for example closure or yeah I think that I heard that in closure you felt like problems with stack traces.
they they can be hard to understand because of a lot of magic mapping behind the scenes.
okay and when when you see like a sex race in elixir, and it's going to contain some elixir functions in some Erlang funk.
and then maybe again some Alex your functions, and that's all very natural.
because those are all ultimately like Alex your programmer you treat them as Alexia functions.
and this Erlang programmer it through them as or lung functions they're the same the same concept.
yeah so it wouldn't be confusing to a person that is writing a lick sir.
if they see something about air lying in a stack trace it's just gonna be another function in your stack trace.
so like imagine like you're calling the library so you're gonna see some functions which you obviously didn't write.
but there's not gonna be a lot of them because there is not some magical layer of mapping from say one paradigm to a different paradigm. or those sort of sort of things.
so obviously were gonna have some functions you always have some code which runs underneath you.
but it's going to be at least in my experience it's it's fairly easy to understand.
and it's again it's just you treat it as if it's elixir.
okay thanks so what are the advantages of the elixir and airline, why do people choose elixir and airline over the competition.
that depends on many people I've heard all sorts of stories, people tend to like like one feature or some features the concurrences for example.
a very big story in Erlang canal and elixir -, and I hope we're going to explore this today in more details, so that's definitely the one thing.
some people just go because they want to try functional programming, some people like it because it's fun.
but in my personal like opinion and this is what I would have said at the beginning.
and it's what I usually say is that language and the runtime the beam they are focused.
they're focused on a particular problem and challenge, that challenge is building arbitrarily complex and scalable software systems.
and in my opinion if that's your challenge then at least year or Erlang are a great tool for the job.
I would say arguably maybe even the best that you have available today.
what we know so far is that err Lang and elixir are general purpose, but they have this sweet spot for concurrent systems that are really complex.
and you're you're spending out a lot of different things.
and so we also understand the relationship between elixir and airline go bids that they're very they're very tightly connected.
but what I'm wondering what listeners may be wondering now is what was the need for a new language elixir.
like why did why did a new language need to be built to get the benefits of the airline runtime.
yeah this is this is a very good question, obviously I'm not the creator of elixir so I'm just gonna explain it from my own point of view.
so our long is by all means great like it has a great tradition.
and it has been built I think the implementation started or the initial prototyping as early as mid 80s or so.
and they have used it since early 90s for mid 90s in production, so it's very well battle-tested in various systems large and diverse.
and it has proven capacity to power complex and scalable systems.
but arguably I would say if we thought I was using plain Erlang since 2010.
so at the time when elixir wasn't even hasn't even began to be developed.
and there are things that are great about her lung, and there are things that were maybe at the time not so great or maybe stuck in some previous times.
and I would say that those those were not like super big issues, but it was a bit hard to start working on our lungs.
so especially back then in 2010 there was much less literature.
there was definitely Joe's book and maybe some other resources, but not as much as you have available today.
the tooling was definitely not as as good as it is today.
so it was sometimes even hard to figure out what should I use to build my projects and to build a deliverable.
and then I would say in particular for me a language, so I have to say that like Erlang as the language it is very simple. it's one of the simplest languages I have ever seen.
people tend to say that Erlang is like but that's not the case, the syntax is strange for most people because it's based on Prolog.
but once you get past that syntax it's a very simple language very regular no not so much rules in the language.
but I would say that this is at the same time the problem of our lung.
because because the language is simple as a developer I - right much more cold.
so I have to I have I don't have so much tools in the language to manage the complexity of the code.
so that was like my personal impression, and I mean in my opinion elixir strikes those problems.
and it actually I would like to say it's that kind of shallow, but this this is probably how I would convey it.
it's like a more approachable or like that's not all about the links here.
but it's definitely one thing which I feel especially compared to the Erlang which I knew from like eight years ago.
so it's very easy to start with the links here, and you can really make your projects pretty quickly.
and you can then deepen your knowledge as you go along, you can refine it.
a lot of effort has been invested into documentation and the tooling around the language.
a lot of effort has been invested into making error messages user-friendly.
so like when you see an error message you actually get some pointers about what you should do to fix it.
and then in the language itself elixir adds some features which allows allow us programmers to organize our code in a better way.
most notably this is the meta programming feature of Alex here or elixir macros.
but there are some other things in the language too some are like smaller pieces some are maybe more in bigger change changes.
but at the end of the day as a developer who has used and has has been using both languages for a couple of years.
I personally feel that I I can move more easily and I can work more easily with elixir.
but as a consequence elixir is definitely more complex language than our lung itself.
I see one thing you mentioned is that the tooling is improved.
and you said that they're like the build process or the build tool had been introduced is that mix or something else.
so Alex you always had to build tool, and it was always mixed since since I remember like I started with Alex here in early 2013.
it was before 1.0 and already mix was a thing.
that or Lang for example when I started with Erlang in 2010, so Harlan currently has a tool which is called rebar 3.
okay and this is now the official building tool, but back then I'm not really sure maybe there was rebar or maybe the ribbon wasn't that kind of completely remember.
but at one point when I found out I found out about it it still wasn't sure whether I should use it or not.
so it wasn't official it wasn't anything built from erickson or included in the release.
there are some other other tools like II make or something like that, and people were using different sorts of things.
and many people were just using plain make to build stuff.
and then it was also not clear whether I should use these concepts of OTP to build my system or not.
so things were like pretty wait for someone who came to Erlang and had no prior experience and that's just my impression.
yeah but as far as the lecture is concerned mix is definitely the tool which we used to start our projects to build our projects.
and to bring them on to deliverables.
so deployable artifacts from your description it sounds like a big part of the reason for.
people adopting a lick sir might be the documentation as you mentioned.
like it just became clear that here's how you can do things, here the tools you can use here the patterns to follow.
and just became clear what the right way to do things was is that a fair summary.
well I mean again people come from different reasons, I think that many people for example come just because at least superficially looks like Ruby.
and I can tell you immediately that it looks like Ruby, but it's way closer to Erlang superficially just it looks like Ruby.
but for people I guess it's okay they they have some sort of familiar thing and they start with that.
and then they discover along the way that they actually can read Erlang and that it's not at all hard.
but what you said about documentation is really in what I would say for example this is really a good reason why you would want to come to lick here.
although I have to say that Erlang has great reference mutation in my experience.
so really when I want to look something up in Erlang a reference it's always there like it's you have a lot of fine prints.
and details and everything is there.
but as a tutorial I personally didn't really find our Lange documentation so good.
I would say that the leaks here has in my impression better story here, especially when it comes to onboarding beyond just the documentation.
you have getting started guides the official ones on the language side, and I totally recommend starting with those.
like even as a book author I tell to people like go to the elixir sites grab those getting started guides and start with that.
and then if you really want to dive deeper then you maybe want to read a book or two or more.
but those guys are really very well written and very approachable.
now is a large part of the airline community migrating to elixir from air lang, or is the story different.
is it like just the community is growing more because of elixir or what's the situation.
yeah well I don't have official numbers obviously, I can only speak of my impression.
so I would say that people who have been working with are long and are proficient with it.
they mostly don't really migrate to Alex here or maybe partially do some stuff in elixir.
but they are have their own ways they are happy they know the the material and they are very familiar with Erlang. and there's really no reason for.
them to migrate then right.
we actually had the story at AER o'clock when I joined their cloak about four years ago.
there was already a lot of code base written in Erlang everybody was fluent in Orland.
and then even I didn't push and say like let's go to elixir.
because that would require a lot of rewrites or you would otherwise have to maintain to code in two different languages.
and that's always more complicated than having just one language.
however I also definitely someone who has been in the community or using Erlang and following the communities since before the elixir existed.
my impression is that there the elixir draw drew more people a lot a lot of people to this world of beam ecosystem as I like to call it.
so both Erlang and elixir and there are other languages like listed for Erlang and alpaca and so on.
so I will definitely say or I feel that the list here definitely brings a lot of people to the whole ecosystem.
now that we have an overview about elixir and and no high-level what it is, let's talk a little bit more about the details.
you you mentioned a few interesting things already, you said that superficially elixir looks a bit like Ruby, and I had a bit of that impression too.
because when I look at the code like the function definitions they look like Ruby, I don't see any type annotations anywhere so there there's that aspect to it.
but on the other hand elixir and Airline are compiled, so is elixir a statically typed or dynamically typed language.
no elixir is dynamically typed language just like Erlang,
which is in my personal opinion arguably the biggest downside of the language those languages.
but it's very unlikely to be changed.
I think that there are some experiments trying to do like maybe limited being facing languages which are typed, but for all intents and purposes they are dynamically typed.
however they are of course strongly typed in the sense that types are well-defined.
and you don't have some magical implicit conversions of strings to integer or vice versa or something like that.
and we have type annotations which some people use some people don't, they are definitely a far cry from a proper type system.
but they can definitely help at least in the documentation sense.
and here at airlock we we certainly use those type annotations now.
the compiler can find certain types of errors right like what type of if I compile my program.
and there is an error like what what type of error with a compiler catch.
well I think it's like not a lot as you would of course expect since the languages are ultimately not statically typed.
so I didn't catch like invoking an unknown function, or maybe if you have unused variable then you're gonna get a warning so things like that.
I think syn syntax error of course, and like if you have some dead code which cannot really execute sometimes that can be also reported.
but of course type errors can be caused by the compiler as I've said.
we have a system for type annotations that one is built-in into again into our lung and then by extension Alex here.
and we have some tools for that which can then catch some kind of type errors but not all of them.
or definitely many of them are simply not caught by by the compiler or in the build phase in the tooling phase.
now there's a tool that called dialyzer, I'm not sure is that in a licker tool or an air link tool and and what is that what does it do.
that's exactly what I was talking about, so I have you have your code and you provide type specification.
and what what I mean by type specification to make it more concrete is you have a function let's say it's called get which takes an x and y.
and you can say a function get takes an integer and takes a string.
and it's going to return either a tuple where the first element is okay and the second element is float.
or it's going to return an item error.
so that's like for an example, and then you can use dialyzer.
and dialyzer can sometimes report that either types are not not proper types the types are not properly passed.
or that the return value doesn't correspond to the specification.
so it can find some sort of mismatches, and you don't even need to provide the specification because dialyzer use it sort of in an like informal informal way.
it can it actually in first types on its own.
so yes it can find some errors about type some kind of type errors.
but there are many things that it cannot really detect the special because of the concurrent nature of Erlang.
so it may be for example let's see if this is right,
if I had a situation where I had a function that returned like an integer.
and I try to do something that I can only do on a string like let's say I append a string to the return value of that function.
even without type annotations that's something that dialyzer would find is that right.
that's something that dialyzer might find you might find, so yeah.
I see those kind of errors sometimes.
but to be honest I didn't really even though I use it frequently I didn't really went into the implementation to find out the rules.
so something it definitely finds those kind of errors and I've seen it like at least say on a weekly basis.
okay and sometimes it misses those errors too, so it sort of depends on how exactly they propagate parameters.
and I gotta admit that I'm not completely certain myself about what will detect what it won't.
but it definitely can find such kind of an error like when you pass.
when you try to do a string manipulation on an integer for example like I had this today something similar to that.
okay I said I think this may have been discussed in Joe Armstrong's show.
the way the way that I understood it was that if dialyzer detects an error it is guaranteed to be an error.
but it's not guaranteed to find every error exactly of any particularly type.
yes it's very it's very conservative, and my experience is that it misses many of errors.
so you're gonna have to rely on tests for that like in pretty much any sort of dynamically typed languages or late typed language.
but when it detects something then it's either a problem in the code or in the type specification yes.
okay at least we don't have to worry about false positive reports.
so there's there I have a list of sort of programming language features.
but maybe it'd be better if I ask you what do you think are the most important features.
or like the most salient features of the language that distinguish it from other programming languages.
so for me by far it's the concurrency model and the semantics it has and the guarantees it's provides, that's like the selling point for elixir and Erlang.
now obviously it's quite abstract like you don't want to choose your language for concurrency, that's like you have some end goal in mind.
but the thing about concurrency in elixir is that it's built again it's built for software systems,
it's fine-tuned for that kind of challenge.
and in a software system you have a bunch of things that are running at any point in time.
you handle a bunch of requests you're doing some background jobs periodic jobs you're priming caches invalidating caches talking to external services and so on and so forth.
and I'd like to call all of these things activities in the system, you have like your request is one activity in my request is one activity.
and maybe even as a part of a single request maybe a bunch of other things are happening.
like I'm talking to one database and communicating to a payment gateway and whatnot, and those can also be separate activities.
and the Erlang and elixir concurrency model or the beam concurrency model if you will,
because it's baked into the runtime gives you this lightweight concurrency through processors.
so these are not OS processes these are lightweight small current things.
and you can model all those multiple activities through these processes and you can manage them and manipulate them and you can run them concurrently.
and this will of course give you scalability in both directions, and you.
can isolate failures and get all sorts of nice things.
and it's all very it feels very natural, because as I said I think about a lot of activities happening in the system, and the implementation really follows that.
you have a bunch of activities running in the system, and there are explicit first class things through these processes.
so definitely concurrency in my opinion is by far the most important feature of both elixir and Erlang, and this whole ecosystem of B.
so it's interesting that you said that the most important feature the language was that concurrence.
and you said you called these different things that are happening concurrently in the system activities.
and how how is it that like what are the the language primitives that allow you to create these activities, and and how does that work right.
so it's it's fairly intuitive although obviously it takes some time to get adapted to, you have this thing called process.
and process again whenever I say the word process I mean a beam process or Erlang process or elixir process that's the same thing however we want to call it.
but it's not an OS process, so let's let me give you.
a quick overview.
when you start your system building for example elixir, you start a single operating system process.
and in that OS process you have a couple of threads running by default one per CPU that you have available, and these threads are called schedulers.
and then we have these processes these are the things that we create from our code.
and you literally have at the bottom of it all you have a function called spawn.
you invoke that function and you pass it a lambda an anonymous function.
and with that invocation you have started a separate process like a separate concurrent activity in the system.
and the anonymous function that you passed to spawn is running in that separate thing.
so you start it and you immediately move along and now you have two processes running in the system.
so that's the basic of it all, you can spawn a bunch of these processes as much as you wish they are very cheap.
they have like a few kilobytes of initial overhead for stack and heap and then they grow if needed.
they are completely separate things I like to say that in elixir or Erlang concurrency is the same thing as total separation.
they have nothing in common they have their own stack heap their own flow of execution, they are even garbage collected separately and they share no data.
there is no shared data in elixir, so instead they can only communicate by passing themselves messages.
and the message is an arbitrary piece of data whatever you can whatever term you can construct in the language, and you just send a message to one process.
and the message is stored in the mailbox of that process which can then pull it from the mailbox by using the language expression called receive.
and then it pulls one message and it does something with it.
so for those who are not familiar with this message passing, you can sort of think like think of it like a lightweight version alors being similar to microservices right.
like with microservices you have operating system processes, and they communicate by some messaging for example frequently it can be a REST API or HTTP requests.
and in beam you have this processors this small lightweight and current things, and they also communicate by sending messages.
and that's primary and pretty much the only way how they can work together. so yeah.
it's quite intuitive and we use this processes a lot, as I said they are very cheap you can create like billions of them if you want to.
and what we do is we really like to run different activities in separate processes.
so for example a typical example is when you have an HTTP server library or a framework every single request is running in a separate process right.
so like you make a request I make a request we have two processes running in the system.
and because these processes are completely isolated it means that they can run concurrently they can be running on multiple cores.
also what process have is they have a complete failure isolation.
so if one process crashes due to an unhandled exception all the other processes in the system are going to be running there's no interruptions there.
so therefore if something happens something wrong happens while handling my request your request can still go on.
or we also have this pre-emptive scheduling.
so for example if my request ends up in an infinite CPU bound loop something like equivalent of.
while true if you will your process can still run even on single core systems.
so you get a lot of benefits by thinking in these separate activities and powering them by separate processes.
and this is to me the core benefit of being facing languages.
and this to me the thing that distinguishes all these languages and the random from most of the things available today.
okay so it sounds like concurrency is the most important thing like of the various trade-offs that are being made they're being made.
so that you can have this highly concurrent system and highly fault-tolerant system.
or as like you mentioned that there were three primitives that that made up the concurrency model.
spawn for creating a new process which can be done frequently and is cheap.
and then sending and receiving it sounds like sending and receiving are to certain extent also cheap says a trio.
well do an extent, so when you're sending what you're really doing is you're copying the data.
into the he poured into the memory space of another process of the receiver.
so like if you had a lot of a large data which are sending say a list of billions of items.
then it's obvious not going to be cheap neither in terms of speed neither in terms of memory.
but it's the same again you think of it as built-in microservices when you're issuing an HTTP request there is some cost some private association to it right.
and if you're issuing a huge payload then obviously it's going to be a bigger price.
in beam this is of course everything happens within a single OS process.
or if you're you can also run distributed beam have a cluster of our land nodes or leaks your nodes and then things happen over the wire.
but when we talk about a single node system then it happens in memory in many cases it's fast enough especially.
if you optimize or if you pay attention to your protocol.
so you don't want to be overly chatty you don't want to send needless pieces of data to another process.
and you want to design your protocol these semantics and this property that data is being copied.
there are of course some exceptions some internal optimizations where the data is in fact not copied but there are some reference counting mechanisms.
but those are I would say mostly implementation details which you mostly don't care about.
so yeah.
there is some cost associated to sending spawning is done within microseconds I think so it's pretty pretty fast operation.
you brought up the fact that airline can also be run in a distributed cluster.
and in that case is there a difference when I send a message to a process that's on my machine or versus another machine or how does it work.
yeah so so a particularly interesting aspect of Erlang is that you're really distributed from the day one even if you're running on a single machine.
so in Erlang distribution and concurrency is one and the same thing, that's a very interesting design decision.
and so you're dealing with a lot of or at least some of these challenges whenever you start working with in with Erlang garlics here.
now when we're talking about multiple nodes what happens is so let me backtrack a little bit.
when you spawn a process the result of the spawn invocation is a thing called pit or process ID.
this is the thing which uniquely identifies a process in the system.
and in order to send a message the process then you use the speed you invoke a function send you pass it bit as the first argument.
and the piece of data are sending as the second argument.
now appeal you can identify a process in the same node which means in the same operating system process in the same beam instance.
but it can also identify a process running on some other nodes in a cluster.
so you somehow connect multiple beam instances into a single cluster.
and then you can spawn processes on other nodes in the cluster and you get the pit as the result.
and then your programming model or your communication pattern is exactly the same, you don't really know whether that process is running in the same instance on another instance.
so in many parts you are already distributed from day one, and in many parts the cold doesn't change at all whether you are distributed or not.
obviously when you are actually using multiple nodes and some network things are going to come through.
so things are going to be slower because the data is then.
serialized and propagated over the network.
and there are more chances of having Nets plates and things like that.
but you can also have those situations even in a single node setting.
I want to talk I want to talk more about macros because that's something that you brought up earlier.
and I think it's pretty important to the language design of elixir.
but it may be like it's better to talk about pattern matching and.
the clegg in the context of the distributed programming or I'm sorry concurrent concurrent programming.
so in elixir when you receive a message the way that it looks to me.
and the code is that it's almost like at the end at the end of the function you are you you just write receive.
and the process is then just waiting it's kind of idle until it receives a message that matches one of the patterns that's in that.
receive statement.
perhaps we should explain what pattern matching is and and how it works.
mmm yeah the pattern matching is many things it's used in many different context, like at the simple simple example is it's destructuring of data.
so you have a complex data let's say it's a tuple for example of three elements it has full bar and buzz.
and then you can write an assignment expression or something which looks like an assignment expression.
you write curly brace X comma Y comma Z close curly brace equals tuple which is the three element tuple. and what happens is then.
X is going to have the value of foo Y is going to have the value of bar.
and that is going to have the value of our bus.
so that's a simple example of pattern matching, and it's quite expressive you can do all sorts of deep nested match's change matches and so on and so forth.
and we use it in many different language expressions or constructs if you will.
so for example one of them is a function invocation or.
function function definition sorry, so you can specify a pattern as an argument to a function definition.
and what happens then is when you invoke a function the argument is matched against the pattern.
and if the match is successful then the function is invoked if not then you get an error.
and you can have multiple clauses of the same function, so you like you define the function with the same name multiple times using different patterns.
and then based on the arguments which are invoked one or another Clause is invoked.
or you can have more than two clauses so you can think of it like a switch if you will.
you sort of declaratively say like if this function is called with argument X being 1 then do this.
and if it's called with X being the value of 2 then do that and so on and so forth.
in the context of the receive expression receive is sort of like receive + switch case if you will.
so you have the receive expression and it basically says I want to wait for a message I want to pull one message from the queue.
if it's already there or otherwise I'm gonna wait for a message.
so you write receive and then you write the clauses you list the patterns to the messages you're interested in.
and you then for every pattern you specify the code which you want to run.
so you can say like if I get a message for example get.
then I'm going to pick take some value which I haven't I'm going to send it to the other side.
and if the message is store then I'm going to take the value which has been passed to me.
and I'm going to store it somewhere in my own process in some kind of a state.
so that would be like an example. so yeah.
pattern matching is really used both in the functional aspect of Alex here as well as concurrent aspect when were when were awaiting messages and handling them.
so being used in the functional aspect of elixir did you mean in terms of functional programming and functional programming patterns.
or just in terms of in how the functions are defined and how they're how they're invoked.
right so yeah.
I should definitely clarify this, so it's I think important to stress that elixir and or lung there are basically two different paradigms in a single language.
so they both have the functional programming aspect and the concurrent aspect, whereas where concurrent is in my opinion definitely much more important.
and I think even at some point Joe Armstrong said that we should stop calling Erlang a functional programming language.
we should call it concurrency oriented programming language because that's what it's all about. so yeah.
you have these two aspects, so you use concurrent programming to organize your runtime again as I said you want to run different activities in separate processes.
and that's your organizing the things that are happening at your runtime those different runtime activities, what functional is at the core of it all.
so within a single process a week series functional programming language, it's not pure functional programming language so you can have side effects.
but it is functional in the sense that there are no classes and objects, and you have first-class functions and data is immutable so you cannot change data.
and functional programming is then.
used to organize your code to organize different concerns,
and to model some domain some piece of problem which doesn't involve concurrency.
and yes we definitely use pattern matching a lot both in this functional aspect.
so when I'm modeling some sort of domain or some sort of problem or even solving like those fairly simple problems for from advent of code for example.
then we use a lot of pattern matching to either decompose our data or to branch on different conditions and so on.
support and it can all in many cases look very declarative in its nature it's quite elegant in my experience.
so I should maybe say that I came to Erlang from object-oriented languages, and I never did any functional programming before.
and this pattern matching really is quite intuitive to to get accustomed to it it was one of the easier parts.
so it's used in a functional aspect, and is definitely of course used in a concurrent aspect of the language -.
you said that in a sense the case statement is like a switch statement.
at the part of the receive that has a pattern match will also contain a case statement I believe is that right.
so it looks like this you have received in elixir.
you have received and then you have some pattern arrow and some code another pattern arrow and some code and so on and so forth.
so it's one it's it's an expression to be technically correct we don't have statements, but yes so receive is basically received and a branch if you will.
you can of course there is like catch-all or a match all pattern which you just list the name of variable.
so I will have like receive X and then I'm receiving whatever comes first right.
and there are similar sorts of pattern matching as you mentioned and the function clauses as well as in the case statement.
and I'm wondering if those are all in some way related.
yeah and if it has to do great pattern matching so it really goes through every or many pores or many aspects of the language.
you also have it in assignment even some tests are relying or or can help you use pattern matching to to test or.
verify some things.
and yeah yeah there are they're used throughout many constructs and many these pieces or parts of the language.
another thing that you'd mentioned in our ROV overview section was meta programming and elixir and macros.
maybe this is a way for us to jump over to meta programming and macros.
because I that.
some features in elixir are actually built using the meta programming functionality of the language itself could you could you talk about that. a bit.
yes that's that's quite interesting because a lot of elixir is built in elixir itself.
which includes some things like if expression for example or unless those are like elixir macros.
you can find the code and you can read the elixir code of if.
and that that's very neat I'd say beyond the plain academic curiosity in that it makes it easier for people to contribute to the language right.
because you don't really needs to learn or Lang to contribute to elixir, there is like a very small core of the language which is written in or lung itself.
now let's take a step back and talk a little bit about what it is, so at least your meta programming allows you to run elixir code during compilation time.
you can write some functions and invoke them during compilation, and you can do some computations.
like take some a great example is for example how elixir builds his string module which deals with all sort of Unicode characters.
so it has a Unicode txt file or something like that which has all the definitions of these characters.
and the code of the string module which is written in elixir plane elixir it reads that file during compilation.
and then it somehow generates elixir code based on that file, so that's one interesting example.
Phoenix the what framework also is based a lot on meta programming.
and it also builds sort of deer cells and allows us to be like more expressive code to route our requests throughout the system.
so it's used in many many sort of different parts like of the language and of the of some frameworks as well.
so the way it works is you can define like as as you are writing elixir code you're writing functions that those are playing functions.
and you can also write a macro and a macro is an you're cold too like you can use a regular elixir expressions.
but the specific the specific of macro is that it's invoked during compilation time.
so what elixir does is it first compiles I'm gonna simplify it a bit but the way it works is it first compiles like this macro code.
and then if there is some other piece of code invoking this macro then it's going to invoke that macro in or during compilation at compile time.
so and then the macro has the opportunity to inject some code into its calling site, and it can use elixir to do that.
so you have like a lot of expressiveness in how are you going to assemble the generated code. so yeah.
that's like some sort of theories it's all very I would say this macros.
and meta programming in a League series arguably the most difficult parts of the language at least in my opinion.
but it's also very powerful and it can help you build some user-friendly DSL.
and it can help you make some compile time optimizations like the one which I mentioned with Unicode where elixir literally when you're installing elixir from source or otherwise.
if you're taking pre-built binaries this thing has been built once and the bulk of the computation has happened at compilation time and it just works for everyone.
so that's also quite a nice benefit and fenix makes some similar optimizations too.
and it can bring down some decisions to compile time because of Alex here metaprogramming there's a lot there.
I think perhaps metaprogramming and.
even Phoenix would be topics in their own right maybe we can we can talk a little bit more about Phoenix later.
but I'd like to drill into metaprogramming a bit more now.
at the top of a elixir module there's a module definition and and a bunch of.
and then within the outermost scope of a module there are a bunch of functions.
but usually at the top I'll see a list of imports and requires.
and I was wondering what were the difference what was the difference between import and require, and I think that require has something to do with meta programming and macros.
they both sort of have to do require is definitely at the core of meta programming.
so again let's just clarify so that everyone can follow us Alex your code consists of modules and functions.
so you have functions and those functions on our organizing modules which could be thought of as a kind of a namespace.
so as I said meta programming allows you to invoke some code during compilation time.
so let's say I have module our foo and a1 invoke function from module bar at compilation time or macro if you will.
so how does the compiler knows that it needs to first compile bar and then foo, and the answer is that we do it with require.
so require if I wanna invoke something from bar info at compilation time up there on time but compilation time then I say require bar.
and this is like a hint to the compiler that it first has to compile bar.
and then bring it to be available in my own context of the module for.
so that's required imports goes beyond that, so import is required plus it lexically imports everything that is public in a bar.
so when I say import bar I implicitly require bar.
and also whatever public function and macro exists in bar is going to be available as.
if it were my own internal function so I invoke it without the module graphics.
ok so that's like a convenience if you will that you don't have to if you frequently involving some functions from another module then you can import it.
so you don't have to always have graphics bar dot this bar does that and so on and so forth.
sorry I can maybe add just one example you have a special module called kernel in Alice your standard library kernel contains a bunch of functions like abs for example.
or absolute number send/receive and so on and so forth.
all of these exist in the kernel module, and the kernel module is automatically implicitly imported into every module that you define.
if it wasn't the case then you will have to write kernel dots and kernel dots on and so on and so forth,
so that's a practical example of importing.
so in an elixir program I might see okay let's as a programmer I'm looking at some implementation code in my own elixir module.
or or save my colleagues elixir module.
and I see a bunch of function and vocations.
the first thing I do is is look within this module and see okay is this a function that is defined within my own module mm-hm.
and if it hadn't been defined there it must have been imported precisely either implicitly because it's part of the kernel module.
or I must have had an import statement at the top of the module precisely yes that's exactly the case.
okay on the other hand if I wanted to use like an enum dot sort function.
I might have required enum or do I need to even require it at all if I'm if I'm referring to advise namespace.
so if you're using enum not sort in at runtime then you don't have to require it at all.
and at compilation time now I have told me that I'm not really sure.
you don't have to I'm pretty sure that you don't have to even require it at compilation time because it's a language module.
but if you've had your own module something which you wrote like let's say my enum for example.
and I wanted to invoke some function from my enum during the compilation of my module then I would have to require it.
I just want to clarify that the distinction here is between run time and compile time, so if I wanted to invoke my enum dot sort from a different module.
so I mean I'm in my own separate module and I want to invoke my enum dot sort at run time I don't need to require or.
import anything.
but if I wanted to invoke it at compile time then I would need to require it.
okay so then the distinction there is it's kind of like we have to know something about like what's happening at compile time versus what's happening at run time.
so just to clarify most of the time like when you're writing regular function and you're writing the code that's happening at runtime that's your regular runtime.
but then you can also write code outside of the function in the module body.
and that code is being then invoked during compilation time as your module is being compiled.
and you can then what can you do there you can compute some value like some constant, and then you can use that constant from your function code.
and what happens is that constant is computed during compilation, and it's baked into your compiled code.
so you effectively move the computation to the compilation time does it make sense.
yeah they make that make sense, this may be this has some some practical considerations too.
I saw that on Twitter you're having a discussion about runtime configuration versus configuration that's baked into your application.
so may be that this might be a situation where or that that comes into play.
yeah it's sort of related yeah it's sort of definitely related to.
because the current configuration mechanism is also being invoked at compile time which has its pros and cons in my opinion it's more cons that pros for that particular thing.
and I'm personally arguing that you should define or derive or compute most of your configuration at runtime because that gives you maximum flexibility.
so even for example invoke or grab your configuration from external storages such as always environment at CD vault database and so on and so forth.
which is obviously something you cannot do at compile time right.
because frequently the build machine is not the same as the machine the system he's running right right right. so yeah.
so to maximize flexibility and configuration you'd want to be able to define or change things at run time versus compiled time.
so it sounds like at least that is very least it's something we have to be mindful of.
if we're writing a liquor code to know what's happening at run time versus compile time.
well for the most part again you don't you write regular release here and you pretty much are you running stuff at runtime.
but there are cases when you have to be mindful yes.
so I just don't want to scare people off like when you start with elixir you mostly don't deal with meta programming initially.
you're maybe the user of it but you're not really even aware that it's working like that and you're just writing plain old regular runtime codes.
so and then when you dive into that thing when you want to do those compile time stuff you have a lot of support from the language there.
and it's going to then require you to be mindful about those things.
but initially you can go a really long way without doing meta programming.
and many people will say like Chris McCord who is the author of the Phoenix framework and the author of the elixir metaprogramming book.
he will say that like the first rule of the meta programming club don't use meta programming.
so you really want to reserve it for those special cases where it can bring you a lot of benefits.
but when it can help you it can help you a lot in many ways.
got it maybe I need to ask one more question about require and import.
because coming from other programming languages I'd be tempted to use the import statement like just.
if I want to like let's say I don't want to have to refer to the sort function by its namespace.
like let's say I was using enum sort would it be a good idea to do that.
or is like I saw that there's also a alias keyword that I can use does that give me another way of referring to the sort method.
or does it just let me change the namespace or can I just get it without the namespace.
if I don't want to care about like if his enum before versus some other collection sort.
well let's start with import first,
so that's like I would say it's sort of depends on on the personal tastes and preferences what I tend to do.
and like that are at air o'clock what I think most of us are doing we are mostly avoiding import in most cases.
because import really makes things implicit and harder to track.
so for the example you mentioned you could import enum and then you can just call sort that sounds very neat.
because you don't have a lot of noise and clutter in the code.
but the problem is then when you import a bunch of such modules then.
it's really hard to track what are you actually invoking.
so personally for enum I would never import it but never really it's short for characters.
and you write enum dot sort and then it's clear for everyone to see what what's actually being involved.
the experience of reading the code is much more easier.
because things are explicitly stated what are you invoking is it a private function is it a well-known function from the inner module.
and in contrast when Isis just sort my first thought would be that this is some internal sort which does things otherwise or somehow decorates the the official one.
and then I would have to browse to the code and then I see okay it's not sort.
then I have to look through the imports and then I can see okay it's the official sort.
so it's a a lot of distraction in the reading experience.
now we have the alias so it's worth mentioning that in elixir modules you have this feeling of a hierarchy.
because you can have a dot or a period character in the name.
so you can have full dot bar dot pass and this is a module name, it is how we build some sort of informal hierarchies.
it's not really like any sort of first class hierarchy there's no special relationship between safe foo.
and food at the bar there is just a character in the dot is just a character in the name.
so the way we tend to organize elixir code you will quickly end up with like three level or four five levels of hierarchy.
so then calling food bar dot bus dot some five action can be really noisy right.
and this is where alias can help you because alias allows you to shorten that name.
it can also allow you to rename a module but we mostly use it to shorten the module name.
so you can state at the beginning of your mod module alias food bar dot bus.
and then in the rest of the module you can just write bus instead of the full qualifier if you will.
so that allows you to give you.
some sort of a trade-off between still hemming and explicitly with the module but in a shorter form.
okay so it doesn't let us remove the module completely so we just have Boz live that it Boz is the function name.
no you can only do that with the import.
okay so so in summary don't do it like don't use import just a shortened the name it's not worth I guess the the confusion.
but but alias is there if you want to get things down to just like the single namespace.
yes in in most cases there are always exceptions.
so yeah.
as I said kernel is Auto imported then Phoenix will import some stuff which really makes sort of sense if you will.
I don't know with our codebase sometimes when you write a helper macro which is used frequently.
then we also import the module too so we don't have to prefix it.
because like we know within our team that what is that thing, but for the most part you wanna I would say you want to avoid import.
and alias is something we frequently use to sort of make the code less noisier.
and another nice benefit is it then you have listed some typical modules which are used at the top of your own module.
if there are a lot of I mean I think elixir is an interesting language just even in the details.
there there are other things that we could talk about like for example tail recursion and tail call optimization that's a cool feature.
we could talk more about immutability and I think we already mentioned that.
but I think if listeners want to know more about the details I think your book does a really good job of talking about the building blocks of elixir.
so what I'd like to do now is move on towards more of the the higher level concepts and talk about thinking like an elixir programmer.
so from that point of view how do elixir programmers think, how do you start designing a program in order that those that level building block.
okay that's quite a broad question, so I can obviously want to say how I tend to approach the problems.
and I'm gonna refer back to what I said earlier that you have two dimensions of the language.
you have the functional elixir and you have concurrent elixir.
it took me a while to figure it out but these days I always first start by sort of pre meditating.
and designing whether in my mind or on a piece of paper what things are functional aspects and what things are concurrent aspects.
then because like in elixir you always have you can think of like concurrent stuff these processes this this concurrent programming are the things which are. then managing the functional parts of your system.
so concurrent is sort of like a higher level runtime organization, and functional is how you transform data and manipulate with it.
then I mostly tend to start with functional aspect first, so I flesh out this is going to be like a single functional thing which runs within a single process.
and I'm going to first model this functional thing, and then I'm going to work on a process structure and I'm going to make it have some processes around it.
so to make this more concrete I can give you.
an example of what it is like the last week.
we had to implement some caching structure for some expect expensive computations.
and it's a bit special because we want to do this caching immediately so we start our systems.
and we have a bunch of database columns for which we want to compute some statistics.
so for each column we have to execute a couple of queries and those are potentially expensive queries.
and we don't want to run them on demand when we need the result of the computation.
we want to compute this data when the system is started so we have it readily available.
so there is a notion of a queue right, we have to form a queue of available database columns, and then one by one we start issuing our queries.
and whenever we compute something about the column some statistic of it we store it into internal cache into some internal in memory table.
that's one part of the problem, and another part of the problem that in in the middle of this caching the database structure might change.
and also in the middle of this caching someone might actually need the result of a column which is at the end of the queue.
so we need to promote this to the top of the queue and that's rough for the problem.
yes so you have a couple things going on, so you're trying to build some data to display some one ear in your application presumably.
but to get that data you've got a number of different queries that have to individually be done and then assembled together into an answer.
but in that time frame some of the data backing those queries might change, and these would also be reflected in the answer.
yes that's that's the part of it, and then again we are building status --tx for each column in the database.
and we are doing it one by one because we don't want to overload the database.
but it might happen that as a user you make some action and we need to promote the column which is maybe at the end of the queue.
we need to promote it to the top of the queue because we need that that call him to actually get to the results.
so what I did there is after first thinking about it I decided to implement a functional data structure which gives me this kind of a queue.
so it's a queue where I say start from the queue with these items.
and then I can invoke a function which says these are now the new items of the queue.
and it does an intersection it discards the non-existent items otherwise keeps the the ones which are existing,
and this functional data structure also gives me a priority feature.
so I can say I start the queue with the column one two and three.
and then I can say bring me the column three to the bring me the column three to the top of the queue. it has to be like in a priority mode.
okay so it's built in a purely functional way it's an immutable data structure.
it has a functions which instantiated and functions which can then do all this transformation on top of it.
and this is what it first and indeed test for that, and it's like of structure which is tuned to our own needs of this particular caching cue.
and then on top of that I have built a process which then actually drives the thing, so it's a separate process which maintains this structure.
and it receives messages from other processes when something changes in the database structure, and it receives messages whence clients needs to promote some column to the queue.
and it uses this functional structure to then actually perform the job, so that's sort of a division of having a functional aspect first and then a process aspect first.
and I'm keeping it simple here, ultimately we also have other processes which revolve around this Q and the caching structure.
but this is the general idea the way I like to think about it.
I want to split what's functional and was concurrent, and then I start usually with a functional part because it's the functional part really means it's a sequential code.
so functional is not no longer divisible into multiple processes and I write that code that test it, and then I make concurrent processes which orchestrate around it. so it sounds a bit way but yeah that's the idea.
okay I think I think we can use this example to talk about some other aspects of how you architect your system in elixir.
but let me just see if I can if I can summarize a bit the the Q you're talking about.
in this case it's just a data structure, we're not talking about like a message queue or something that usually we think of as active.
yeah it's a first in first out data structure where we can promote some things to a high priority mode.
okay but then there is an active part of your system that's using that data structure to decide like how to prioritize and.
execute different resize.
yes okay but I think it it it also illustrates something you said in your book about how elixir can simplify an architecture.
because if you designed this system in another language ecosystem you might have had a different moving parts right.
you might have you might have actually used a message queue mm-hmm that was a separate message cueing system.
or you might have you might have actually had the cat cache as a separate layer in your architecture could you talk about that.
exactly so my impression is and that's been like even before leaks.
when a user along in my first project Moeller to medium projects I'm almost positive that elixir relates to a simpler architecture.
because it can give you.
a lot of these built in solutions for things like have keeping queues in memory caches handling requests concurrently and so on and so forth.
and in many cases you can like especially simpler cases you can just have your solution completely built with elixir like a simple example is my blog.
so my blog is powered by Phoenix it's written in elixir it's a single project it's a single process it runs completely multi-core.
it has some things beyond just serving articles it has some internal analytics it does registration with let's encrypt that's also done in Alex here.
I mean I'm using search bot as a tool but the orchestration is done in the mixer.
and I need exactly one operating system process there is no nginx or Apache or any other sort of reverse proxy involved.
and it's a very simple solution.
and such has been my experience not only for that blog but also for my first like more involved project which are built in Erlang.
and for the things that we do at airlock.
and that that has a lot of benefits it brings a lot of benefits when your structure is more homogeneous.
and when you don't need to run a bunch of different and multiple operating system processes powered by different technologies.
so this obviously simplifies your operations instead of managing five or six or I don't know how many different processes.
and tools and technologies and components you mean you're managing maybe one or two.
but also means that there are less things to learn like say a junior developer comes to the project they learn elixir.
and already they can touch every part of the system.
which is not the case if you have like some key value third-party caches and message queues and a reverse proxies and whatnot.
those are all separate pieces of technologies that need to be understood.
like if you learn a leak here it will not help you to learn and stay nginx configuration it's a completely different kind of things, so there's benefit in that.
there's benefit in local development you just I just started my project there is the command how you start your mix project and everything is running locally.
I don't have to juggle with a bunch of these other things running in the system.
there's a benefit in testing because everything is highly integrated and homogeneous then it's much easier to test everything.
and yeah there are a lot of benefits in all phases of software development which primarily come from the fact that you have this powerful concurrency mechanism.
and you can build a lot of stuff natively directly in elixir or Ireland without needing to resort to third-party tools.
now I want to mention or I wanna stress that we of course we use third-party tools.
if the challenge is complex we're going to reach for third-party tools we are not afraid of that.
we don't want to reinvent complex wheels.
so I don't know in my experience very frequently we tend to use SQL databases for example.
or any other third party database which is a really mature project product which you don't want to reinvent yourself.
we sometimes use nginx too it's a good tool it does the job.
and sometimes it can help you I don't know people use EDD I have used that CD at some point.
and people use elixir with kubernetes so we definitely use those other things.
but the threshold for stepping outside of our main technology is much higher there's much less need for us to do that because we have a built-in solutions.
and if our problems are simple like I want to manage some key value in that I really don't need a third party product.
we have a great tooling directly in elixir for that.
for example the same thing holds for message queue for managing load during load regulation the rate limiting pipeline parallelism and all sorts of things.
and this is really where the benefit in my opinion lies for elixir and airline, the pitch line would be that your technologist it will be simpler.
and that's going to make it easier for you to operate that system to develop it to test it.
and to onboard new developers and these are huge benefits I would say for n is crucially.
the simple architecture is also something that scales right, it's not just that it's simpler but you can handle way more traffic.
but yeah like do you reach a certain point where this scale becomes an issue.
and then how do you how do you deal with it just can can you then start breaking things out into a more heterogeneous system.
does does elixir play well in a heterogeneous environment where you start to add like proxies or elixir play is definitely with all these other technologies.
so you you have a bunch of them you have net like drivers written in elixir.
there are a couple of different ways how you can run or integrate or encode like code like code written in other languages in your elixir based systems.
so you can either run them in process or out process.
so then you can use leaks here as a sort of controller plane which orchestrates all these activities most of which are still implemented in elixir.
and some of which are maybe running in other languages.
for example at earplug we have some parts of our system written in rust for some critical thing.
and not a lot of parts but we have some parts written in rust and that works natively for us.
but we still start Alex your project and then the elixir project starts the rust thing.
previously in some previous incarnation of our system like about three years ago we were running Lua interpreter in C.
and we were using that to power some Lua code.
so you can definitely integrate in all sorts of ways, and as I said people definitely put reverse proxies in front of elixir when it actually make sense.
so by opting for elixir you are not confined to this world of elixir line you can step outside.
and use a lot of other things in many different ways when the need for that arises.
yeah here the perk the part that you mentioned that I thought was interesting was that you can use it for orchestrating a lot of these different parts.
so it's it's good for the concurrency and managing I guess hierarchies of different activities that are happening mm-hmm, but what does it not good for.
well I would say that the elixir is definitely or longer not really suited if you wanna ship one of two to a bunch of different clients.
like say you're writing a command-line tool not for yourself or for your team but for like a wider audience.
it's going to be a huge pain to actually deploy that to a bunch of different unknown operating systems.
and the deployable itself will be like very large.
this is for example something where I think go has a really great story in term of this.
a single deploy binary which you can build for many different target platforms.
also elixir is very well it is known for elixir and Erlang that they are not really super fast.
when it comes to raw processing like number crunching for example doing some heavy computations.
so if you're doing something like that you're probably better off writing that critical piece of your system in say C C++ or rust or some other language.
and then integrated into your elixir system.
I think there were examples of for example video transcoding platforms written in Erlang.
and obviously you don't want to re-implement the video manipulation yourself you have a mature library like ffmpeg for that.
besides beyond being just mature the library is also very fast, and you will not be able to reach that same level of speed in native elixir Erlang.
and people are using that and then they're orchestrating these activities of their users which are actual than I don't know submitting videos.
and they are orchestrating their cues in elixir and or lungs.
so the implementation of just the transcoding stuff is done in sea in the well-known existing library, and then you're orchestrating that code from your elixir for example.
now there are a couple ways that you can do that, you said that you can do it either in process or out of process what's the difference.
you can do it in process you can run for example in process see some other things too I think also rust can be executed in process.
the problem with in process is that you can do all sort of nasty things to the beam.
you can break guarantees basically by running for encoding process the fundamental guarantees of beam are off the table they are non-existent anymore.
so if you have a seg fault for example in your foreign code like say in C then you crash the entire beam instance.
and then you lose the fault tolerance properties of Alex run or line.
another example would be if you your foreign code ends up in the infinite loop like CPU bar loop it completely blocks the scheduler.
and you can completely paralyze your system.
so those are the problems of running in process.
obviously the benefit is that there is no special marshaling of the data, so everything is in the same OS process so it's going to be more performant.
and therefore those those things are usually done for something which is really some small and limited pieces of functionality.
like say if you want to implement the first memory FS the 2d matrix library for manipulation.
or you want to maybe expose some machine learning functions which are implemented in some other libraries, then you want to run those things in process probably.
for doing things outside of process you pay a little bit of price in terms of communication overhead.
because data has to be some of serialized on one and deserialize on another end and vice versa.
but you get fault tolerance because how it works is you start this external OS process from or lung or elixir.
and then you communicate with it as if it was elixir processes if it was the little bean process running in your system.
and if it crashes you don't crash but you're gonna know.
so you get those fault tolerance exactly the same as if you have them with native Alex here so that's a big benefit there.
and that approach is usually used when you have like a bigger chunk of work that you can do in the external things.
so like I'm going to send it a message and then it's going to maybe get the data from the database.
and it's going to crunch that data so it's going to do a lot of processing.
this is a great candidate for running things outside of process because the communication overhead is that not so big.
okay so there are some options and any outlined some different perhaps some thinking that we can apply like into Howie when we make the decision.
it sounds like for the for the most part it's very sounds very scary too I guess to import foreign code into elixir unless you really know what you're doing.
there are a lot of considerations it sounds like into how you make the decision of how to use the foreign code.
so yeah.
I'll link to your blog posts about foreign processes and and how you make some of those decisions, and will refer to that in the show notes.
so what are some examples of successful projects that are using elixir like just elixir or long.
because you have of course a lot of projects using or long whatsapp is arguably the most famous reference there.
my impression as far as Alex here is concerned that the Bleacher Report they are the sports sites you know in the United States.
I think they claim they are like the second largest maybe I didn't hi hope I remember it right.
so they are there as far as I know one of the biggest elixir users.
otherwise they are like tons of I don't know other companies that are using it smaller or large.
I think that Pinterest was using it for something yeah I would have to double-check the whole list.
but a bunch of people are using it for all sorts of things.
yeah why was it successful in those projects in your opinion.
well people always from what I gathered like some other external reports people of course always have a lot of praise for the concurrency again.
many people came from different backgrounds like from other languages very actually I've had to fight the concurrency.
and the same story holds for me too, and once you come to Ireland that thing can really flow.
and it can really help you build systems which are able to deal with larger volumes.
but also systems which are more fault tolerant and somehow more stable in production.
they sometimes even refuse to crash or refuse to completely terminate like in my experience this sometimes happens even.
if I don't pay attention or pay particular attention to it the system somehow survives.
so I would say that this is like the the biggest draw the biggest thing that draws people to elixir.
I have seen that many people in particular with the leaks here mentioned that it was quite easy to get started with it, you don't necessarily learn everything at once.
but I think the approachability story in elixir is really really great, and people report that they are able to become productive within the first week.
so they can write some code and move further, and then they refine the knowledge as they go along.
so I think that's also a very important piece of the puzzle.
and this particularly well where elixir is very helpful are people usually starting with the Phoenix framework.
when they are using a Luxor and your experience or are they just going with some other lower level functionality.
well I've seen cases of both so it sort of depends I guess on the nature of for how you want to approach the technology.
I've seen many people starting with Phoenix and I think it's a valid approach you you sort of get something going something tangible.
and visible early in the game and that's rewarding right and you see the feedback can you see some progress at the concrete.
on the other hand there are people who like to just first start with the language.
and they just want to ignore completely those other things like the framework and the other libraries.
and they just want to start from the bottom and work their way until they get those higher-level things.
I think that either approach is fine it depends on your personal preferences.
I would probably say that many people do come to elixir through Phoenix or start with Phoenix directly.
and that's all quite quite fine there are excellent getting started guides for Phoenix too.
so if you want to start like that immediately one start with web development I would say go to the first two dimensions mix your language a guides.
so you get some basic feeling of the language, and then go to the Phoenix getting started guides and just work your way through these tutorials which are really great.
and you will have something going and you will be able to work to produce some code to be productive, and then you can refine your knowledge later on.
I mean at some point probably you're gonna have to look into some deeper resource whether it's a book or a video or some series of blogs or whatnot.
but you don't need to necessarily read all those volumes upfront you can start pretty quickly and easily.
I want to call out a few resources for listeners that will be in the show notes.
the first is on that topic of top down with Phoenix versus bottom up.
I thought you had a very helpful and informative article about that very topic on your blog so I'm gonna put that in the show notes.
and the other is that you had an architecture description for how you are using a lick sir at hair cloak.
and I think that might be informative for people as well so I'll put that in the show notes too.
I think that the last topic that that I had I think it's relevant for what you said about how the elixir provides fault tolerance.
and I want to try to understand the relationship between fault tolerance and scalability, and how that how that works in a lick sir.
well that's an interesting question, so I would definitely say that the mechanism for achieving both is the same in elixir and Erlang.
so we use processes or views concurrency to get scalability and also to get fault tolerance.
so the way it works is again I always have to come back to this mantra which I'm calling run different things separately or run different activities in separate processes.
and you want to have like in smaller systems you can easily have like thousands few thousands of them.
and in larger systems maybe hundreds of or maybe even millions of them running in some extreme cases.
so if you have a lot of processes then you're giving a lot of potential to your virtual machine to beam to spread that load across available course.
and obviously then you're immediately vertically scalable like say you're running on a two core machine and.
you're reaching for example say 90% of your capacity of your CPU resources.
you take the system you put it on a bigger box with more course and it just spreads its wings and literally scales because you're in internally harlequin currents.
so that's vertical scalability and you get that out of the box, and I've actually had the cases of such scaling like immediately in my early or long days.
another thing that concurrency gives you is potential for horizontal scaling, because you can spread those processes around the cluster right.
so you can start with say two nodes or three nodes and maybe add another node and have some library which actually does the spreading of those things. and you can scale horizontally.
this story is not so seamless so it's definitely there's definitely room for improvement in terms of higher level libraries which make these things easier.
but it's again rooted in concurrency, and then finally we come to fault tolerance, and fault tolerance really works well with any powered by this concurrency.
because as I mentioned a failure of a single process does not disturb anyone in the system right.
it looks like a novice process a process crashes there is like a division by zero square root of minus one.
or some kind of an error like that you get an exception a process crashes.
and but everybody everything else keeps running without any interruptions because there is no shared memory the crashing thing left no garbage behind for other processes to be corrupted.
and finally the third piece of the puzzle is that a crash even though it's not an abrupt event it's also not a silent event.
any other process in the system can be notified about a crash or any process in the form of a message.
so I could get a message like if I'm a process I get a message process foo has terminated because of the reason bar.
and then I know what has happened.
and then I make this decision I can make some decision like maybe I'm going to start another fool.
this is coal also the supervisor pattern where the system heals itself.
or maybe I'm going to take the role of the fool myself when it's down.
or maybe I'm going to take myself down because my work doesn't make sense if foo is not running.
so these are quite simple primitives, we have some higher level represent op of this.
and they allow you to structure your program in a way where you separate individual actions and you separate crashes.
like if something happens and it's in one process it will not disturb any other process, so this sort of guides your decisions about how to split things across processes.
like a typical example is let's get back to the cash story you're populating a cash from the database, and you're managing a key-value cash in some process.
you're gonna have two processes at least one which actually read stuff from the database, and another process which keeps this stuff in memory.
the reason why you have two is because if the reader crashes which it might.
because it maybe talks to an external database oh there's networking and that's always flaky and can fail.
you can still so if the database rating fails you still have the process which keeps the data in memory it's still there in text right.
so you have separated failures.
so that's an example of how you can think in fault tolerance with concurrency.
okay so the thing that's trying to retrieve data from the cache if it crashed it wouldn't also cause the entire cache to crash for example exactly.
yeah that's a very simple example here you can have like more elaborate examples, so and I had one example when I was reading from a TCP connection.
I had to parse the data and then do something with it.
and it involved a bunch of processes like I had just one process which was just reading it established a TCP connection it was just reading bytes.
and forwarded them to another process.
and what you get by this is whatever else fails down the line you still get to keep your connection open.
and then I had like a pipeline of five to ten processes which would do this microphages of the whole pipeline.
and the fault tolerance so it was brilliant I was like super surprised how easy it was to get it and how stable the program that was.
because you get whatever fails it's a micro failure.
you if you're running thousands of things are millions of things then one failure really doesn't make all that big of a difference in the grand scheme of things.
most of your system is running.
and this is what you want to have in a software system.
because you wanna provide service to the most of your users most of the time right that's the philosophy.
I see so the philosophy of airline of letting things crash when they have errors and restarting carries over into elixir.
and because you just let those failures happen you try to handle it you end up with overall a more more stability.
and yes yeah you don't give me red hairs right.
so let it crash is it sometimes wrongly I mean it's a catchy term but it's something of my play maybe misunderstood.
let it crash is really what it really means is it means fails fast.
so when something is off in your system like some preconditions are not satisfied or what or what not you're gonna race and you're gonna just let the thing crash.
but you're not going to let everything crash.
the idea is to split your system into these small micro pieces which you can then let crash because no one is in fact too big to fail.
so that's very important piece of the puzzle.
got it okay thanks for that clarification, so you said that airline allows you to have any process be notified if another process fails.
and you said that this part of the supervisor pattern.
I've seen some in elixir code I've seen some instances where you have specified a supervisor and different supervisor strategy.
so is this that the higher level rapper that you're talking about.
right the supervisor is definitely a higher level thing, because it's implemented in plane or lung, and you could reimplemented yourself in plane elixir which is like a nice exercise.
and yes the supervisor what it does is you basically tell it to start one or more processes.
and it asks the runtime to be notified if those child processes terminate no matter why the terminates.
so then the supervisor gets a message like child foo has terminated the reason bar.
and then it will do something it can either restart the child or it can restart all the children or it can restart just younger children.
so the one which are depending on that child this is what you specified with supervision strategy.
like how it will handle the case of a child which needs to be restarted.
I think we covered the basic building blocks, and if people want to know more I think your book is a great resource elixir in action.
and maybe maybe now is a good opportunity for us to talk about how people can find out more about you your blog your book.
and any resources and dates that you wanted to mention.
okay so your book has been in Manning's early access program.
and I think it's it's either being released now or it's gonna be released soon as that right it's in the production phase.
yes so it's going to be released but I have no clue about the dates, so things don't move super fast meaning we didn't have hope two or three months.
okay so possibly within the window of when to when the this podcast is published, but it's available for early access now.
and I was able to read it through Manning's early access program and just get the book online. so yeah.
that's I think a resource that I found to be really really informative.
and of course your your blog your Earl Angelus I'll put that in the show notes too, was there anything else you want to mention.
well like in spoken word maybe no I can send you a bunch of links.
I have compiled some and some which came to mind as I was as we were doing this talk.
so I could compile the list and just send you the links which you can include in the show notes I think that's fine.
okay then Sasha it's been great having you on the show, and for software engineering radio this has been Nate black thanks for listening.
thank you for having me here it was a pleasure my pleasure thank you.
thanks for listening to se Radio, an educational program brought to you by Triple E software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at SE - radio net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter or through our slack channel at SC radio.com.
you can also email us at team @ SC - radio net.
this and all other episodes of se radio is licensed under Creative Commons license 2.5.
thanks for listening.